The cell radio in your device operates roughly like this.
From an initial idle state, it takes a couple of seconds
to turn on until it can start transmitting. That kind of
latency makes for a sucky web browsing experience. So rather than
going back to idle, state machine stays on at full power
for a certain amount of time. Typically, around five to ten
seconds before dropping to an intermediate low power mode that uses
less battery than full power, and has lower latency to return
to full power than the standby mode. If a new
transfer is initiated, the radio will be promoted back to
full power mode. And if nothing happens for another period
of time, typically around 30 seconds to a minute, it'll
drop back to standby. The exact latency in tail times
varies between carriers, and even in carriers between states and
countries, as they try to balance low latency with longer
battery life based on factors like cell congestion and typical
prevailing network conditions. So the exact timings vary. How
do we optimize our transfer frequency? Ultimately, it doesn't matter
what the specific timings are. You just need to
understand that the network is going to attempt to balance
low latency with high battery life. For us, when
it comes to planning out data transfers, we really like
to be somewhere around here,. Now, if we return
briefly to the cell radio state machine, we know that
every time we perform a data transfer, the radio will
stay active for at least another five seconds of full tail
time, and anywhere from 30 seconds to a minute at low
power before it finally returns to standby. That means every time
you initiate a transfer, you're powering the cell radio up for
at least 20 seconds. So let's take a look at how
that affects an app, using the little cookie approach. An app
like this can drain the battery without even having to transfer
much data. Each of these small peaks is
an app pinging its analytics back to the server,.
In this case, every 15 seconds. These logi-peaks represent
intermittent data transfers based on user interaction. For example,
they may be viewing a restaurant listing or looking
at tomorrow's weather forecast. Beneath it, we've graphed how
this affects the radio state. The blue shows active
data transfers. The red, the radio in full power.
And yellow showing low power mode. The gaps in between, if
there were any, indicate when the radio was idle. So while
this app is running, what is the percentage of time that
the cell radio is able to go back to its idle state?